American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIe. 1845-1865 APS.Archives.IIe APS.Archives.IIe
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Regarding the geology of the Missouri valley., July, 1861; 12-1/2x8; Hayden, F. V. (Ferdinand Vandeveer), 1829-1887
    [ca.]. D. 6p., end. For printed article on this subject, see APS Trans., n.s., XII, 1ff.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, July 1, 1861; 10x8
    Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: W.H.Miller. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions
  - Letter to J.P. Lesley, July 4, 1861; Lawson, George
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Aug. 9, 1861; 11x9; Botanical society of Canada
    Kingston, Canada, L.S.: George Lawson. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Aug. 9, 1861; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Massachusetts Historical Society
    Boston, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Robt. C. Winthrop, Pres.and Nath.B.Shurtleff, Libn.1p.,end.: E.O.K[endall]. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the President of the A.P.S., August 12, 1861; 4 1/2" x 7"; Reese, John J. (John James), 1818-1892
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Tenders his resignation from membership in the A.P.S. See Pro., VIII, 279.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Aug. 16, 1861; 8-1/2x6-3/4; Essex Institute
    Salem, Mass., Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Henry Wheatland. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Aug. 24, 1861; 9-3/4x7-3/4; New York State Library
    Albany, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: S.B.Woolworth. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Aug. 30, 1861; 10x8; Chicago Historical Society
    A.L.S.: William Barry, Sec. 1p.,end. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Sept. 3, 1861; 10x8; Boston Public Library
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s B. Trego, Sept. 13, 1861; 8x5; G. & B. Westermann Brothers
    New York, L. 1p. Directions for shipping Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Sept. 16, 1861; 10x7-3/4; New York Academy of Sciences
    New York, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Robt. Dinwiddie. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Sept., 1861; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Yale University
    New Haven, L.S.: Theodore D. Woolsey, Pres.and D.C.Gilman, Libn. 1p.,end.: J.L.LeC[onte]. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to Cassius M. Clay, October 11, 1861; 8 1/2" x 10 7/8"; Wood, George B. (George Bacon), 1797-1879
    Copenhagen, 3 pp. A.L.S. Copy. Concerning application of A.P.S. to the Russian government for a copy of the printed edition of Tischendorff's manuscript of the New Testament.
  - Letter to [J. Peter] Lesley, October 16, 1861; 8 3/8" x 10 13/16"; Wood, George B. (George Bacon), 1797-1879
    Copenhagen, 7 pp. A.L.S. Report of his travels and activities on behalf of the A.P.S. while abroad. Account of Certain foreign members. Concerning penguins.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, November 4, 1861; 8 3/8" x 10 13/16"; Wood, George B. (George Bacon), 1797-1879
    Breslau, 3 pp. A.L.S. Has received letter from U. S. minister to Russia, Mr. Cassius M. Clay, assuring him that the Russian government will send a copy of Tischendorff's New Testament to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Ben[jamin] Gerhard, Port Royal, S. C., November 13, 1861; 5 1/8" x 7 7/8"; Du Pont, Samuel Francis, 1803-1865
    3 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents an Atlas of the state of South Carolina, by [Robert] Mills, to the American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Parker Foulke and others, December 3, 1861; 7 13/16" x 9 7/8"; Hayes, I. I. (Isaac Israel), 1832-1881
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. Accepts invitation from A.P.S. to communicate "the scientific results of my expeditions."
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s B. Trego, December 24, 1861; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Gilliss, J. M. (James Melville), 1811-1865
    Secretary of A.P.S., U.S. Naval Observatory, Washington, 2 pp. and endorsement. L.S. Requests set of A.P.S. Transactions and Proceedings for library of the Naval Observatory. See Pro., IX, 2.
  - Twenty-six receipts for annual contributions to the American Philosophical Society, 1861-1865; 2 3/4" x 6 3/4; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 26 slips. Cha[rle]s B. Trego, Treasurer.
  - Letter to J. P. Lesley, Jan. 21, 1862; 10-1/2x8-1/4; United States Naval Observatory.
    Washington, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: J.S.Hubbard Libn. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, Philadelphia, Jan. 21, 1862; 9-3/4x7-3/4; United States Naval Observatory.
    Washington, A.L.S.: William B. Whiting. 1p.,end. Thanks for packages of books from the APS and is delighted that the observatory is to receive APS publications.
  - Minute book..., Feb. 8, 1862 - Sept. 26, 1896; 8 1/4" x 13 1/4"; Linnaean Society of Lancaster County, Pa.
    249[45]p, Manuscript Beginning with meeting of Feb. 28, 1874, the minutes are clippings from newspapers with ms. additions. Contains also printed constitution of the Society, and news clippings relative to decease of members, etc. Not found May, 2011.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, October 23, 1862; 5" x 7 7/8"; Cohen, Joshua J.
    Secretary of A.P.S., Baltimore, 1p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents two photographs "of the Paper Currency of former days" to the A.P.S. See Pro., IX, 92. for Photographs unknown collection under "money"
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, April 17, 1863; 5" x 7 15/16"; Trego, Charles B., 1794-1874
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. A.L.S. Recommends Professor [James] McClure for membership in the A.P.S.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, May 12, 1863; 4 7/8" X 7 3/4"; Leidy, Joseph, 1823-1891
    Librarian of A.P.S., [Philadelphia], 1p., address and endorsement. A.N.S. Requests that cast of skull of masasaurus be delivered to bearer to be deposited in the Academy of Natural Sciences.
  - Report of the special committee on the lease or sale of the hall, July 17, 1863; 8" x 12 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. and endorsement. D.S.: F[rederick] Fraley, Franklin Peale, Jno. F. James, Edward King. In re negotiations with the city of Philadelphia for rental or sale of the hall.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Aug. 7, 1863; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Troyon, Frédéric, 1815-1866
    Lausanne, A.L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to the Secretary of the A.P.S., October 3, 1863; 4 1/2" x 7 1/8"; Scott, Robert H. (Robert Henry), 1833-1916
    Dublin, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. The secretary of Geological Society of Dublin requests missing numbers of A.P.S. Proceedings and Transactions.
  - Letter to F[rederick] Fraley, November 17, 1863; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Otto, William T., 1816-1905
    L-12 Department of the Interior, Washington, 1 p. A.L.S. Has delivered articles of agreement for sale of certain property of the A.P.S., together with a brief of title to the same, to Theodore [F.] Stokes.
  - Letter to F[rederick] Fral[e]y, November 17, 1863; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Stokes, Theodore F.
    Washington, 1 p. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of articles of agreement for sale of certain property of the A.P.S., together with a brief of title to the same. Deed missing.
  - Letter to the Secretary of A.P.S., December 12, 1863; 7 5/8" x 9 3/4"; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Smithsonian Institution, Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. L.S. Requests loan of ethnological specimens belonging to A.P.S., to be used as models by the Smithsonian Institution. See Pro., IX, 281. FILM 235 FRAME 26
  - The law in the form of continents and oceans, 1863; 12-3/4x8; Reichenbach, Oskar
    ca. A.D. ca. 103p. Cf. APS Minutes,May 18,1866. Enclosed originally in letter from Reichenbach to Dana; April 1, 1865.
  - Author index to Catalogue of the American philosophical society library, 1863-1884; American Philosophical Society
    432p. F. (Manuscript) n.d. Mss. f.p. no.1.
  - Dei risultamenti attenuati da una nuova analisi, Feb. 3, 1864; 9-1/2x14-3/4; Zantedeschi, Francesco, 1797-1873
    dello spettro luminoso; D. 34p. In Italian. Enc.of 2 plates illustrating spectral experiments. This is a ms.copy of Chapt. III of his Ricerche fisico-chimico-fisiologiche sulla luce..., Venezia,Antonelli,1846,pp. 47-79.
  - List of subscribers to the catalogue of the Library, Feb. 19, 1864; 12-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, D.S.by 19 men. 1p.and end. and envelope.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, Feb. 23, 1864; 11x8-1/2; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    [Phila.] A.L.S.: Joseph Leidy 1p., end., and end. Concerns transfer of Academy's archaeological collection to the A.P.S. Refers to Peale Stone Age relics.
  - Receipt of the Curators of a deposit of minerals and fossils belonging to the A.P.S., March 28, 1864; 12x8; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    A.D.S.: Joseph Leidy 1p. and end.
  - Report of the committee in relation to a site for a future hall for the Society, May 6, 1864; 4 3/4" x 7 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. A.D.S.: Eli K. Price. Concerning possible purchase of a lot on the south side of Penn Square, owned by Mr. Harrison.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Aug. 31, 1864; 10-3/4x8-1/2; Bataviaasche genootschap von kunsten en wetenschappen
    Batavia, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: W.Stortenbeker, Jr. 1p. In French. Gives directions for mailing publications.
  - Letter to Ch[arle]s B. Trego, Treasurer of A.P.S., September 10, 1864; 5 1/4" x 8 1/4"; Law, Edward E.
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. A.N.S. Tenders his resignation from the A.P.S. See Pro., IX, 414.
  - Report of the committee upon... the purchase of a site for a hall, October 3, 1864; 7 5/8" x 9 7/8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: Eli K. Price, Stephen Colwell, F[rederick] Fraley. Recommend that A.P.S. purchase Mr. Harrison's lot.
  - Letter to the President of the American philosophical society, November 30, 1864; Wood, G.B.
  - Report of the special committee to whom was referred a paper on the fossil flora of the United States, by Leo Lesquereux, February 3, 1865; 5" x 8"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: Tho[mas] P. James, E[lias] Durand, B[enjamin] H. Coates. Publication in Transactions recommended.
  - Letter to [James D.] Dana, New Haven, April 1, 1865; 12-1/2x8; Reichenbach, Oskar
    London, A.L.S. 3p. Enc. Asks that he read the enclosed and have it printed in Silliman's journal. Gives history of the article. Asks that he forward it to Lesley if it is not printed. For enclosure, see: Reichenbach. The law in the form of continents...; ca.1863.
  - Letter to J. B.[Peter] Lesley, Philadelphia, April 18, 1865; 8x5; Weichert, Charles M.
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, July 10, 1865; 4 7/8" x 7 3/4"; Porter, Thomas C. (Thomas Conrad), 1822-1901
    Lancaster, Pa., 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of fifty copies of communication on Indian rocks. Linnaean Society of Lancaster has resolved to make a complete set of casts of figures on Indian rocks, the same to be presented to the A.P.S. See Pro., X, 149, 255.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, July 19, 1865; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Smithsonian Institution
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Oct. 1, 1865; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Académie royale des sciences, des lettres et des beaux-arts de Belgique
    Brussels, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Quetelet. 1p.,end.: J.L.LeC[onte]. In French. Thanks for publications.
  - Letter to J. P[eter] Lesley, Philadelphia, Nov. 23, 1865; 10-1/2x8; Bataviaasche genootschap von kunsten en wetenschappen
    Amsterdam, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: C.T.Matthes. 1p.and add.,end.: J.L.LeC[onte]. In French. Thanks for publications.
  - Letter to Messrs. Trego and Leslie [sic] Philadelphia, Dec. 13, 1865; 7-1/2x6; Society of the United Brethren for Propagating the Gospel Among the Heathen
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. H.A.Brickenstein. 3p.,end. Asks for return of documents deposited in the APS library by Heckewelder.
  - Letter to [J. Peter] Leslie [sic], Philadelphia, Dec. 27, 1865; 12-3/4x8; Reichenbach, Oskar
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Asks him to bring his article to the attention of the APS. Cf. APS Minutes, May 18, 1866.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Dec. 28, 1865; 10-3/4x8-1/2; Smithsonian Institution
  - Report of committee appointed to consider the application of "x y z" for the Magellanic premium, 1865; 10x8; American Philosophical Society
    [ca. ?]. D.S.: Rob[er]t Briggs and Pliny E. Chase. 3p.